Guide to the Oxford Tobacco Research Station Records
Oxford Tobacco Research Station Records
circa 1909 - 1984
1909 1984
Oxford Tobacco Research Station
MC 00492
The collection contains sixteen boxes of textual documents and photographs from roughly 1909 to 1984 that pertain to the Oxford Tobacco Research Station, which is just outside Oxford, North Carolina. The bulk of the collection consists of annual research reports from these years (unbound 1909-1947; bound 1948-1965). The annual reports detail the research conducted in the areas of agronomy, botany, entomology, engineering, and pathology. In addition to these reports, the collection also includes correspondence from the 1930s and 1940s, manuscripts and news releases from 1920 to 1984, and research files from 1911 to 1961.
The Oxford Tobacco Research Station is located one mile west of Oxford, North Carolina, the county seat of Granville County. It was established in 1912 as a joint program by the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) and the North Carolina Department of Agriculture (NCDA). Over the course of a century of research on tobacco, the Station gained an international reputation as a leading center of tobacco science under the direction of project leaders in Agronomy, Botany, Entomology, Engineering and Pathology. Notable research accomplishments include fertility investigations concerning tobacco plant nutrition, development of the first tobacco varieties with resistance to Granville Wilt and black shank diseases, and the invention of tobacco bulk curing barns.
8 linear feet
16 archival boxes
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Gift of Paul Peterson, 2013 (Accession 2013.0234)
This collection is arranged in four series: Annual Reports, 1909-1965; Correspondence, 1930-1943; Manuscripts and News Releases, 1920-1984; and Research Files, 1911-1961. Within each series, materials are generally arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by subject.
The Oxford Tobacco Research Station is located one mile west of Oxford, North Carolina, the county seat of Granville County. It was established in 1912 as a joint program by the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) and the North Carolina Department of Agriculture (NCDA). Over the course of a century of research on tobacco, the Station gained an international reputation as a leading center of tobacco science under the direction of project leaders in Agronomy, Botany, Entomology, Engineering and Pathology. Notable research accomplishments include fertility investigations concerning tobacco plant nutrition, development of the first tobacco varieties with resistance to Granville Wilt and black shank diseases, and the invention of tobacco bulk curing barns.
The collection contains sixteen boxes of textual documents and photographs from roughly 1909 to 1984 that pertain to the Oxford Tobacco Research Station, which is just outside Oxford, North Carolina. The bulk of the collection consists of annual research reports from these years (unbound 1909-1947; bound 1948-1965). The annual reports detail the research conducted in the areas of agronomy, botany, entomology, engineering, and pathology. In addition to these reports, the collection includes correspondence from the 1930s and 1940s, manuscripts and news releases from 1920 to 1984, and research files from 1911 to 1961.
Correspondence is primarily between station staff, government officials, professional researchers, and tobacco farmers. Most is from the 1930s, but some letters date to the early 1940s.
Manuscripts and news releases include drafts of research publications, copies of newspaper articles about the station's activities, and pamphlets to be distributed to North Carolina farmers. E.G. Moss, an agronomist and early superintendent of the station, wrote many of these materials. Most date from 1920 to the 1950s, but some news articles were published as late as 1984.
Research files include data from tests and experiments conducted at the station, as well as information on field days and other events that the station held for the public. Relevant correspondence is occasionally included with the files. The bulk of the files date to the 1930s and 1940s, but the full range of the series is from 1911 to 1961.
These materials show station staff's commitment to providing North Carolina tobacco farmers with information on tobacco diseases and with advice on best agricultural practices. Materials also show staff's partnerships with official and academic communities to disseminate research conclusions.
Oxford Tobacco Research Station; Peterson Paul; Oxford Tobacco Research Station; Agricultural innovations; Oxford (N.C.); North Carolina Research Tobacco
- Annual Reports, 1909-1965; 1909 1965
  This series contains the bulk of the collection: annual research reports from 1909 to 1965 (unbound 1909-1947; bound 1948-1965). The annual reports detail research conducted in the areas of agronomy, botany, entomology, engineering, and pathology. Unbound reports are less formal in structure than later, bound reports, and they often appear to have been enclosed in correspondence between station agents and superintendents. This correspondence, where extant, is maintained with the reports. There are no reports for 1910, 1911, 1912, 1913, 1947, 1958, and 1960.
  This series is first arranged chronologically, and then alphabetically by subject if more than one report exists for a given year.
  - Annual Reports, 1909; 1909 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1914; 1914 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1915; 1915 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1916; 1916 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1917; 1917 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1918; 1918 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1919; 1919 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1920; 1920 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1921; 1921 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1922; 1922 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1923; 1923 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports - Agricultural Leaflets, 1923; 1923 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1924; 1924 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1925; 1925 1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1926; 1926 1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual Reports, 1927; 1927 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports, 1929; 1929 1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1930; 1930 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1930; 1930 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports - Mosaic, 1930; 1930 1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports - Black Fire, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports - Black Root Rot, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports - Crop Rotations, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports - Granville Wilt, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports - Mosaic, 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports - "Sore Shank", 1931; 1931 1931 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1932; 1932 1932 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports - Fertilizer Tests, 1932; 1932 1932 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports - Mosaic, 1932; 1932 1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual Reports, 1933; 1933 1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, 1933; 1933 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Annual Reports - Mosaic, 1933; 1933 1933 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Annual Reports, 1934; 1934 1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, 1934; 1934 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Annual Reports - Root Knot, 1934; 1934 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Annual Reports, 1935; 1935 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, Granville Wilt, Mosaic, Black Fire, 1935; 1935 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Annual Reports - Tobacco Diseases, 1935; 1935 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Annual Reports, 1936; 1936 1936 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Annual Reports - Root Knot, 1936; 1936 1936 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Annual Reports - Black Shank, Black Root Rot, 1937; 1937 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, 1937; 1937 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports - Root Knot, Southern Root Rot, Mosaic, 1937; 1937 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1938; 1938 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, 1938; 1938 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports - Root Knot, 1938; 1938 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1939; 1939 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports - Black Root Rot, Black Shank, 1939; 1939 1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, 1939; 1939 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports - Tobacco Projects, 1939; 1939 1939 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports - Mosaic, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1940; 1940 1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports - Black Shank, 1940; 1940 1940 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports - Data, 1940; 1940 1940 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Annual Reports - Disease Investigations, 1940; 1940 1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports - Wilt Counts, 1940; 1940 1940 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Annual Reports - Black Shank, 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, Root Knot, Mosaic, Southern Root & Stem Rot, Fusarium Wilt, 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports - Wilt Counts, 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1942; 1942 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1942; 1942 1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports - Black Shank, 1942; 1942 1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1928; 1928 1928 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports - Blue Mold, Root Knot, Mosaic, Fusarium Wilt, Southern Stem & Root Rot, 1942; 1942 1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1942; 1942 1942 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1943; 1943 1943 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1943; 1943 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports - Data, 1943; 1943 1943 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports - Granville Wilt, 1943-1944; 1943 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1944; 1944 1944 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1944; 1944 1944 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports - The Year Summary, 1934-1944; 1934 1944 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1945; 1945 1945 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1945; 1945 1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports - Fertilizer, 1945; 1945 1945 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports - Oxford 26, 1945; 1945 1945 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1946; 1946 1946 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1946; 1946 1946 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1946; 1946 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1948; 1948 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1949; 1949 1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1950; 1950 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1950; 1950 1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1951; 1951 1951 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1951; 1951 1951 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1952; 1952 1952 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1952-1953; 1952 1953 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 4), 1954; 1954 1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 4), 1954; 1954 1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports (3 of 4), 1954; 1954 1954 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports (4 of 4), 1954; 1954 1954 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports - Biennial Report, 1952-1954; 1952 1954 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 3), 1955; 1955 1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports (3 of 3), 1955; 1955 1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 3), 1956; 1956 1956 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 3), 1956; 1956 1956 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports (3 of 3), 1956; 1956 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1957; 1957 1957 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1959; 1959 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1961; 1961 1961 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1962; 1962 1962 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1963; 1963 1963 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1964; 1964 1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1965; 1965 1965 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1937; 1937 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports (2 of 2), 1941; 1941 1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports - Disease, 1943; 1943 1943 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports - Burley Tobacco, 1946; 1946 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1953; 1953 1953 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 3), 1955; 1955 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1957; 1957 1957 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports (1 of 2), 1964; 1964 1964 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1930-1943; 1930 1943
  Correspondence is primarily between station staff, government officials, professional researchers, and tobacco farmers. Most is from the 1930s, but some letters date to the early 1940s. These materials show station staff's commitment to providing North Carolina tobacco farmers with information on tobacco diseases and with advice on best agricultural practices. Materials also show staff's partnerships with official and academic communities to disseminate research conclusions.
  This series is arranged chronologically by decade, and then alphabetically by the surname or affiliated company of the sending correspondent.
  - Correspondence - A, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - B (1 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - B (2 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - C (1 of 4), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - C (2 of 4), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - C (3 of 4), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - C (4 of 4), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Clayton, E.E., 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - D, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - E, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - F, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - G (1 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - G (2 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - G (3 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - H, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - K, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - L, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - M (1 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - M (2 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - N, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - O, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - P (1 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - P (2 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - R, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - S, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - T, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - V, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - W (1 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - W (2 of 2), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940s; 1940 1949 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Research Files, 1911-1961; 1911 1961
  Research files include data from tests and experiments conducted at the station, as well as information on field days and other events that the station held for the public. Relevant correspondence is occasionally included with the files. The bulk of the files date to the 1930s and 1940s, but the full range of the series is from 1911 to 1961.
  Materials are first arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by subject.
  - Tobacco Varieties, 1911-1950; 1911 1950 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Division of Agronomy of the N.C. Extension Service, 1922-1923; 1922 1923 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Tobacco Demonstration Work, 1926-1933; 1926 1933 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Tobacco Fertilizers (Urea, Cal-Nitro), 1920s-1930s; 1920 1939 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Agricultural Program for Granville Co., 1930; 1930 1930 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - CWA Projects, 1933-1934; 1933 1934 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - The Culture of Flue-Cured Tobacco in N.C. (Moss & Bullock), 1938; 1938 1938 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Articles for Newspapers, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Blue Mold (1 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Blue Mold (2 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Blue Mold (3 of 3), 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Data, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Fertilizer Tests, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Field Days, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Governors, N.C., 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Rotation Equipment, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Tobacco Research Meetings, 1930s; 1930 1939 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Field Days, 1930s-1940s; 1930 1949 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Report on Station Work and Rental Agreement, 1930s-1940s; 1930 1949 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Reports, Projects, Plans (College), 1945-1947; 1945 1947 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Reports on Station Work and Rental Agreements, 1945-1947; 1945 1947 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Tasks, 1953-1958; 1953 1958 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Tobacco Research (publication), 1957; 1957 1957 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Tobacco Work, 1958; 1958 1958 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Plant Pathology Review, 1959; 1959 1959 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Tobacco Literature (1 of 2), 1960s; 1960 1969 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Tobacco Literature (2 of 2), 1960s; 1960 1969 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Plant Pathology Review, 1961; 1961 1961 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Clayton, E.E., undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Lunn, W.M., undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Report of Federal Activities at the Tobacco Station, Oxford, N.C., undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Summary of Progress of Oxford Tobacco Research Station, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Manuscripts and News Releases, 1920-1984; 1920 1984
  Manuscripts and news releases include drafts of research publications, copies of newspaper articles about the station's activities, and pamphlets to be distributed to North Carolina farmers. E.G. Moss, an agronomist and early superintendent of the station, wrote many of these materials. Most date from 1920 to the 1950s, but some news articles were published as late as 1984. Research publications were often intended for The Progressive Farmer, an agricultural magazine founded in 1886 in Winston-Salem, North Carolina. News articles and announcements were often intended for the Raleigh News and Observer.
  Materials written or overseen by Moss are grouped together and broadly arranged chronologically. Other materials, largely copies of publications, are grouped together and broadly arranged chronologically.
  - E.G. Moss (2 of 2), 1920-1925; 1920 1925 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - E.G. Moss (1 of 2), 1926-1930s; 1926 1939 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - E.G. Moss (2 of 2), 1926-1930s; 1926 1939 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - E. G. Moss (1 of 2), 1920-1925; 1920 1925 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - E.G. Moss (1 of 2), 1940s-1950s; 1940 1959 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - E.G. Moss, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Copies, 1920s-1984; 1920 1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - E.G. Moss (2 of 2), 1940s-1950s; 1940 1959 (Box 14, Folder 1)